BETH: Supporting individuals with
autism to take positive risks in their
lives is not about encouraging them
to do dangerous activities or things.
It’s about getting them to take control
of their lives and make choices and then
learn from the consequences of those
choices whether positive or negative.
Everyone has the right to take risks,
no matter how scary it might be,
especially for those supporting them.
However, there is still a need for
‘safeguarding’ or ‘duty of care’
with all risks that may be taken.
JOE: Risk is a necessary and important
part of life for everyone, but we need
to think about how risk affects those
with autism and manage this risk.
When managing risk, there is the potential
for carers to be overcautious and
overprotective of an individual, depending
on the severity of their disorder.
BETH: By identifying the risks
associated with an activity for an
individual and assessing how that
activity can be completed effectively
and safely, can help them to build
confidence and develop new skills.
Also understanding that there are
consequences to taking risks both
positive and negative, can help to promote
the ability to learn from mistakes.
JOE: Carers can empower the individual
to have a more fulfilling life through
positive risk-taking, and this can
bring real benefits, when it takes into
account the needs and preferences of
the individual and their circumstances.
The individual is then enabled to grow
in confidence, learning from their
experiences, and developing new skills
and abilities, and make full use of
their opportunities and potential.
BETH: Supporting individuals with
autism to take positive risks puts them
more in control of their own lives.
Risk shouldn’t be seen as a negative
experience that’s best avoided as
this can lead to an individual having
a more limited life experience.